<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>J. Haug</title>
 <link href="https://jhaug.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://jhaug.com/"/>
 <updated>2017-03-23T23:27:27-07:00</updated>
 <id>https://jhaug.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Joshua Haug</name>
   <email>josh.haug55@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Wood Finishes, Summarized</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2017/01/02/wood-finishes/"/>
   <updated>2017-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2017/01/02/wood-finishes</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you have ever visited the wood finishing aisle at your local hardware store, you’re probably familiar with the sheer volume of options.
To a newcomer, these options all &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; familiar and seem to be the same thing.  However, different wood finishes provide different protections and have different effects on the appearance of your final project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
Wrote this for myself as a cheat sheet 👍
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stain&quot;&gt;Stain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change the color of wood while leaving the grain visible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doesn’t offer much protection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add mineral spirits to dilute or add multiple coats to intensify&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply with a paint brush or cloth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dries quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raises the grain, so sand lightly in between coats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oil&quot;&gt;Oil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brings out the natural beauty of wood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protect against moisture but are nowhere near as effective as, say, varnish or shellac&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lots of types, including…
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Boiled linseed oil
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cheap, good for decorative things that don’t require much protection (like a picture frame)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teak oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tung oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mineral oil
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Food-safe, so good for items like chopping boards or spoons&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Danish oil
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Offers more protection than other oils, b/c is a mixture of oil and varnish&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Good for things that require protection, like a tabletop&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;polyurethane&quot;&gt;Polyurethane&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plastic coating for wood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Variants include…
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;water-based (dries quickly, doesn’t beautify the wood)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;oil-based (dries slowly, beautifies the wood)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most durable finish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaves a plastic-y feel to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;varnish&quot;&gt;Varnish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Made of oils, resins, solvents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dries slowly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brings out natural beauty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Durable, although not as much as polyurethane&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;laquer&quot;&gt;Laquer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A thin, liquid varnish that is usually sprayed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Durable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dries quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be polished&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brings out natural beauty in the wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shellac&quot;&gt;Shellac&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glossy finish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dries quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to apply&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often used on antiques and fine furniture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not as durable as varnish/poly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dulls with age&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finishing-waxbeeswax&quot;&gt;Finishing Wax/Beeswax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Protects against moisture (indoors only)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brings out beauty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leaves a smooth finish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be polished&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear or colored variants available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply sparingly with a cloth in a circular motion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be re-applied as needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can’t use another finish after wax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About This Website</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2016/10/04/about-this-site/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-04T01:02:23-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2016/10/04/about-this-site</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
How I developed this site.  Guaranteed to be boring for non-developers.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you get math to render on your site?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The math on this site is rendered using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathjax.org/&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt;.  To get this working, I navigated to Jekyll’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_layouts/default.html&lt;/code&gt; and included this snippet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;text/javascript&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Now I can use the LaTeX math format in my blog posts and it comes out as a beautiful equation.  For example, the equation for the aerodynamic diameter of an aerosol particle&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-aerodyn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-aerodyn&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is represented as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$${a} = d_{e}\left(\frac{\rho_{p}}{\rho_{0}\chi}\right)^{\frac{1}{2}}$$&lt;/code&gt; in my code, but produces…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{a} = d_{e}\left(\frac{\rho_{p}}{\rho_{0}\chi}\right)^{\frac{1}{2}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I should just use LaTeXit for this sort of thing, but haven’t had the time to change the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do your code blocks look so nice?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The built-in support for code blocks produced ugly horizontal scroll bars.  To add functionality for code wrapping, I went to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_sass/_code.scss&lt;/code&gt;, found the block that started with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pre {&lt;/code&gt; and added in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;white-space: pre-wrap;&lt;/code&gt;, which did the trick.  If you’re on mobile, however, the code blocks are gonna look ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you make it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I modeled my effort on &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualande.com/jekyll-github-pages-poole&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. In short, I built it using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/poole/poole&quot;&gt;Poole&lt;/a&gt;, which is a wrapper for &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;.  I write the posts in markdown and Jekyll converts the files to HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How are you hosting &lt;a href=&quot;jhaug.com&quot;&gt;www.jhaug.com&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This website is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/joshhaug/joshhaug.github.io&quot;&gt;hosted on github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you set up that SSL certificate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;SSL is not enabled automatically for GitHub pages.  To get https working, I followed the instructions &lt;a href=&quot;https://sheharyar.me/blog/free-ssl-for-github-pages-with-custom-domains/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-aerodyn&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In case you’re interested, the aerodynamic diameter of a particle is the diameter of a spherical particle with the same settling velocity as the irregular particle.  This particle is assumed to have a density p₀ = 1000 kg/m³ where Ꭓ represents the correction factor.  I’m still trying out using footnotes in markdown, so that’s what I’m doing here. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-aerodyn&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Subtle Differences Between Aerosols, Vapors, and Gases</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2016/08/26/clarifications-states-of-matter/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2016/08/26/clarifications-states-of-matter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
The differences between &lt;b&gt;aerosols&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;vapors&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;gases&lt;/b&gt; are subtle, to say the least.  In fact, the differences are practically invisible to the naked eye. Here I clarify those differences, answer common questions, and address popular misconceptions.  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-its-important&quot;&gt;Why It’s Important&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Different processes of generation, different behaviors, different effects on our lungs, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarifies the differences between e-cigarettes, herbal vaporizers, and combustion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The confusion is amplified by the e-cigarette industry’s use of terms for marketing that are not congruent with the science.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gives scientists a clue on how to allow scientific jargon to evolve
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vapor redefinition to the gaseous phase or suspension of a liquid&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;definitions-of-things&quot;&gt;Definitions of Things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Term&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Suspension&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A heterogeneous mixture containing solid particles that are big enough for sedimentation. Diameter ≥ 1.0 µm.  The particles can be either solid or liquid. In theory, all suspensions settle.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Aerosol&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A suspension of liquid droplets or fine solid particles in a gas. Particles can range from 1 to 10 µm in diameter.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Colloid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Unlike suspensions, colloids do not settle.  Diameter &amp;lt; 1.0 µm.  Kind of the gas version of a solution.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Vapor&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;The gas phase of something that was once a liquid.  Colloquially refers to the aerosol produced by e-cigarettes and herbal vaporizers.&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Steam&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;The gas phase of water.  Steam itself is invisible.&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Wet Steam&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Steam itself is invisible, but wet steam is not.  Wet steam is a mist (or aerosol) of water droplets.  It's caused by water vapor condensing in mid-air.&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;definitions-of-processes&quot;&gt;Definitions of Processes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Process&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Sublimation&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;A phase change: solid → gas.  The substance skips the liquid phase entirely.&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Vaporization&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;A phase change: liquid → gas.  Includes such processes as boiling and evaporation.&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;Condesation&lt;/td&gt;
       &lt;td&gt;A phase change: gas → liquid.  This is best illustrated by a cold glass of water &quot;sweating.&quot;&lt;/td&gt; 
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you boil a pot of water on the stove, you’ll see a plume of &lt;strong&gt;steam&lt;/strong&gt;.  However, water vapor is itself &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weatherquestions.com/What_is_water_vapor.htm&quot;&gt;invisible!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What e-cigarettes produce: aerosol (suspension of small droplets of propylene glycol + nicotine solution + flavoring solution)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What herbal vaporization produces: aerosol (small droplets of trichomes)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What combustion produces: 
Solid and Liquid Aerosol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are droplets suspended in the air?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aerosol-categorization&quot;&gt;Aerosol Categorization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aerosols can be categorized by the measure of particle heterogeneity.  For instance, an aerosol can be &lt;strong&gt;monodisperse&lt;/strong&gt; (all particles the same size – this one is very rare in nature) or &lt;strong&gt;polydisperse&lt;/strong&gt; (many different sizes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll be covering polydisperse aerosols, as they are the most common.  It’s useful to describe polydisperse aerosols in terms of their particle size makeup (i.e. divide the total size range into intervals and find the percent of particles that fall within each interval.)  The two most common size intervals you’ll find in literature are PM-10 and PM-2.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PM-10&lt;/strong&gt; is an abbreviation for “Particulate Matter of Aerodynamic Diameter ≤ 10.0 µm.”  These particles deposit in the mouth, throat, and upper parts of the lungs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PM-2.5&lt;/strong&gt; is therefore an abbreviation for “Particulate Matter of Aerodynamic Diameter ≤ 2.5 µm.”  These particles are in the danger zone, so to speak – they are small enough to reach the alveolar region of the lungs, where they can be effortlessly absorbed into the bloodstream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deposition&quot;&gt;Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Deposition is the process by which aerosol particles deposit themselves on solid surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common causes of deposition in human lungs are…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impaction — some particles are unable to follow the curvature of the airflow due to their inertia, so they are flung out of the airstream and hit something&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Settling (aka gravitational sedimentation) — particles fall and settle due to gravity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diffusiophoresis — spontaneous movement of particles caused by a concentration gradient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other (not significant in respiratory system) deposition causes include…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interception — when following the streamline, some of the outermost particles will run into obstacles (note the difference between this and impaction, which is the result of a curvature in the air path)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turbulence — I don’t know this one, but read it somewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermophoresis - (aka thermodiffusion, thermomigration, the Soret effect, the Ludwig-Soret effect) movement of particles due to a temperature gradient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turbophoresis — tendency for particles to collect in the area of least turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electrophoresis - movement of particles induced by a uniform electric field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;respiratory-deposition&quot;&gt;Respiratory Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diameter of the particle dₚ determines the region in which it will deposit.  Size-selective sampling is generally split into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inhalable fraction: enters the nose, mouth, pharynx, larynx (dₚ &amp;gt; 10.0 µm)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thoracic fraction: reaches the thorax/chest region, trachea to terminal bronchioles, corresponding to PM-10  (dₚ ≤ 10.0 µm)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respirable fraction: reaches the alveolar/pulmonary region, corresponding to PM-2.5  (dₚ ≤ 2.5 µm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important mechanisms of deposition in the respiratory system are impaction, settling, and diffusion.  Impaction is of primary concern in the large airways.  Settling is most important in the smaller airways and alveolar region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aerosol-behavior&quot;&gt;Aerosol Behavior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, aerosolized particles may not be spherical.  However, one can approximate a non-spherical particle’s depositional behavior by calculating an &lt;strong&gt;aerodynamic diameter&lt;/strong&gt;.  This is done by pretending that the irregular particle (with settling velocity s) is spherical, keeping the settling velocity constant.  This idealized particle is assumed to have a standard particle density of 1000 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.  The diameter of this new particle is defined as…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;d_{a} = d_{e}\left(\frac{\rho_{p}}{\rho_{0}\chi}\right)^{\frac{1}{2}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where $\rho_{0}$ is the standard particle density and $\chi$ is the dynamic shape factor (a ratio of the resistive force of an irregular particle to that of a spherical particle).&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Fluid Dynamics and Traffic</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2016/04/24/fluid-dynamics-and-traffic/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-24T01:55:21-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2016/04/24/fluid-dynamics-and-traffic</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bet you didn’t know that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trafficwaves.org&quot;&gt;traffic can be mathematically represented as an emergent phenomenon in fluid dynamics.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MBTI© is Junk Science</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2016/01/01/mbti-is-bullshit/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-01T00:02:23-08:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2016/01/01/mbti-is-bullshit</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s a question I get asked from time to time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why does it matter what my Myers-Briggs type is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s often followed by this, usually in a hushed voice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You know it’s bullshit, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jhaug.com/assets/MBTI.gif&quot; alt=&quot;a common search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and perform a web search with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MBTI bullshit&lt;/code&gt; as the query.  You’ll find &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; of people fuming over the MBTI© for a myriad of reasons.  The most common of these are…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weak factual basis&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neither Isabel Briggs Myers nor Katherine Briggs had a formal background in psychology&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Based on binary characteristics, which is too restrictive for personality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jung’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Analytical_psychology&quot;&gt;analytic psychology&lt;/a&gt; is based on anecdotal rather than empirical evidence, and is therefore unscientific&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The tests don’t work&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most people get a different result upon re-taking the test &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-half-diff&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-half-diff&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;hr /&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reinforces stereotypes of personality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Seems like a scam&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;MBTI Trust® has trademarked Myers-Briggs Type Indicator®, Myers Briggs®, and MBTI®.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.myersbriggs.org/myers-and-briggs-foundation/ethical-use-of-the-mbti-instrument/trademark-guidelines.htm&quot;&gt;Here are their guidelines for usage.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Moreover, the bulk of scientific literature pertaining to MBTI is published for conferences of the &lt;em&gt;Center for the Application of Psychological Type&lt;/em&gt; or as papers in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Psychological Type&lt;/em&gt;, both of which are funded by sales of MBTI-related tests and services.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When stacked up, these arguments are pretty convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-importance-of-helpful-bullshit&quot;&gt;The Importance of Helpful Bullshit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I totally agree that MBTI is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; legitimate science, I disagree with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is precisely what should happen to MBTI – it should be demoted.  The scientific community and Fortune 500 companies alike should respect the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the majority of the population has little need for personality categorization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a small minority for whom MBTI serves a valuable purpose.  In the Big 5, these are called BLANK and BLANK.  MBTI classifies them as INTPs and INTJs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classifying people’s personalities is inherently ambiguous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fuels navel-gazing-and-elitism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-then-again&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-then-again&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s an interesting system of classification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most importantly, MBTI crudely describes human behavior in a way that makes sense to awkward people (INTP and INTJ then INFs, ENT, ENF, everyone else) (Dylan 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an INTP. &lt;strong&gt;INTP&lt;/strong&gt;s constitute 3-5% of the U.S. population.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-type-freq&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-type-freq&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  INTPs share some bizarre quirks like a fondness for discordant music and a strong suspicion towards their own emotions.  For more information, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intp.org/intprofile.html&quot;&gt;An INTP Profile&lt;/a&gt; by Paul James.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some INTP sites I’m familiar with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/intp&quot;&gt;INTP subreddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intp.org&quot;&gt;intp.org&lt;/a&gt; has a few cool resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intpexperience.com&quot;&gt;intpexperience.com&lt;/a&gt; goes into depth about the INTP’s relationship with emotion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most online personality forums seem to share the masturbatory “nobody understands us” mentality.  These are no exception – you’ve been warned.  Unlike other forums, however, many commenters express sincere gratitude for the typology.  INTPs often have a hell of a time finding others that they can relate to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jhaug.com/assets/INTP-gratitude.png&quot; alt=&quot;a common post on INTP forums&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thoughtcatalog.com/lorenzo-jensen-iii/2015/05/13-reasons-why-the-myers-briggs-test-is-absolute-nonsense/&quot;&gt;13 Reasons Why The Myers-Briggs Test Is Absolute Nonsense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://skepdic.com/myersb.html&quot;&gt;The Skeptic’s Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/give-and-take/201309/goodbye-mbti-the-fad-won-t-die&quot;&gt;Adam Grant’s critique of MBTI&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cppblogcentral.com/cpp-connect/the-myers-briggs-assessment-is-no-fad-its-a-research-based-instrument-that-delivers-results/&quot;&gt;CPP’s response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-half-diff&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiana.edu/~jobtalk/HRMWebsite/hrm/articles/develop/mbti.pdf&quot;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; for more information &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-half-diff&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-then-again&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Then again, those sorts of people will use any means they can to assert superiority – be it IQ scores, taste in music, what have you. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-then-again&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-type-freq&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This figure comes from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.myersbriggs.org/my-mbti-personality-type/my-mbti-results/how-frequent-is-my-type.htm&quot;&gt;the official Myers-Briggs page&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-type-freq&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Myers-Briggs -- Quality Resources</title>
   <link href="https://jhaug.com/2015/04/07/myers-briggs-quality-resources/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-07T01:02:23-07:00</updated>
   <id>https://jhaug.com/2015/04/07/myers-briggs-quality-resources</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people find it difficult to learn concepts on their own.  Here’s something to think about: does one have a moral obligation to share straightforward &amp;amp; factual resources?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applications of Myers-Briggs (and personality theory in general) to human-computer interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audiovisual folks might appreciate Michael Pierce’s Sixteen Types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keirsey’s first and second works on the subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
